<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[UHK | Ritho's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/category/uhk/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/"/>
  <updated>2019-03-10T23:33:15-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.ritho.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[palvarez@ritho.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UHK Keyboard review]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/uhk/2018/09/15/uhl-keyboard.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/uhk/2018/09/15/uhl-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Short after I came to Mexico to work, in December 2015, I found a project in
Crowd Supply for a new keyboard that draw my attention, the Ultimate Hacking
Keyboard (a.k.a <a href="https://ultimatehackingkeyboard.com/">UHK</a>), and I decided to buy one. The characteristics that
impressed me the most were that it was a mechanical keyboard (I'm a fan of
mechanical keyboards) and, more important, it could split in two halves.
</p>

<p>
After a long wait (its delivery was delayed for more than two years) I can
say I'm very happy with my acquisition. It's not the perfect keyboard, but
it's quite close. The thing I miss the most from the keyboard are some extra
keys, like the escape key or the arrow keys, but, since it's easily configurable
via an agent provided by the company that make them (it's available for linux,
MacOS and Windows, which is something to appreciate), I'll be doing some changes
in order to be more and more comfortable with it.
</p>

<p>
As I suspected, the fact that is a mechanical keyboard make it very gentle with
my fingers, and the fact that I can split it and orient it with several sideboards
make me feel more natural in my posture when I write with the UHK. It also comes
with a wood palm rest that is comfortable for my wrist, and the size is compact
but not too small, so I can move it around from my apartment to my office in
my bag and, at the same time, is not too small that I type several keys at the
same time.
</p>

<p>
I know it's not a cheap keyboard, but the quality worth it, and the agent, the
keyboard firmware and its schematics are free (as in Free Software), so you are
not only buying a great keyboard, but supporting the Free Software and Hardware
movement, apart from a honest business. I also appreciate a lot the good
communication the UHK makers have, since they have shared all the process of
building the keyboard and the different difficulties they have found, it's
not common to find a project that open in all their path from the original
idea to the final product.
</p>

<p>
The only thing I'm waiting now for is the extensions I ordered with the keyboard
itself, one with a trackball to attach the mouse in the keyboard and another
one with three extra keys that I plan to use to define some macros to make more
automatic some recurrent tasks.
</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
