<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[UHK | Ritho's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/category/uhk/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/"/>
  <updated>2020-03-25T02:02:10+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.ritho.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[palvarez@ritho.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UHK Keyboard review]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/uhk/2018/09/15/uhl-keyboard.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/uhk/2018/09/15/uhl-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Short after I came into Mexico to work, in December 2015, I found a project in
Crowd Supply for a new keyboard that draws my attention, the Ultimate Hacking
Keyboard (a.k.a <a href="https://ultimatehackingkeyboard.com/">UHK</a>), and I decided to buy one. The characteristics that impressed
me the most were that it was a mechanical keyboard (I'm a fan of mechanical
keyboards) and, more important, it could split into two halves.
</p>

<p>
After a long wait (its delivery was delayed for more than two years) I can say
I'm delighted with my acquisition. It's not the perfect keyboard, but it's quite
close. What I miss the most from the keyboard is some extra separated keys, like
the escape key or the arrow keys, but, on the other hand, it's easily configurable
via its agent, so I'll be doing some changes to be more and more comfortable with
it. The agent is Free Software, provided by the company that makes the keyboard,
and available for Linux, macOS and Windows, which is something to appreciate.
</p>

<p>
As I suspected, the fact that it is a mechanical keyboard makes it very gentle
with my fingers, and the fact that I can split it and orient it with several
sideboards makes me feel more natural in my posture when I write with the UHK.
It also comes with a wood palm rest that is comfortable for my wrist, and the
size is compact but not too small, so I can move it around from my apartment to
my office in my bag and, at the same time, is not too small that I type several
keys at the same time.
</p>

<p>
I know it's not a cheap keyboard. Still, the quality worth it, and the agent, the
keyboard firmware and its schematics are free (as in Free Software), so you are
not only buying a great keyboard but supporting the Free Software and Hardware
movement, apart from an honest business. I also appreciate a lot the excellent
communication the UHK makers do, since they share all the progress of building
the keyboard and the modules, the difficulties they have found, &#x2026; I can assure
it's not common to find a project that opens in all their path from the original
idea of the final product.
</p>

<p>
The only thing I'm waiting now for is two extensions I ordered with the keyboard.
The first one is a trackball to attach the mouse, and the second one is three extra
keys that I plan to use to define some macros to make more automatic some recurrent
tasks.
</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
