<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[General | Ritho's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/category/general/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-14T19:00:03-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.ritho.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[palvarez@ritho.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm Back!]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2013/09/17/back.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T18:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2013/09/17/back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Hi all!</p>

<p>
I know it hass been more than a year without writing anything, but, between my
absorving work and the fact that I'm not really good with the written world (and
a little bit of lazyness, why no admit it), I didn't found the time to dedicate
to the blog.</p>

<p>
Now I'm not going to give promises, but I'm going to try it hard to write at least
one post per week, and who knows, maybe once I've started to write I can write
more often and more fluently.</p>

<p>
Well, you'll have notices from me during this week.</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Latest adquisitionsn]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2012/03/03/latest-adquisitions.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-03T23:09:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2012/03/03/latest-adquisitions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Hi all!</p>

<p>
I'm back from South America (I've been 6 weeks in Chile and Argentina)
with some good and bad news. The bad new is that I've been stolen and
I don't have anymore some of my technical stuff, like a laptop, an
external hard drive, a tablet and some other things. I've also lost
some information, specially documentation and some projects of my
studies and previous works.</p>

<p>
The good thing is that I've to restore some of the things I've lost,
so I bought a desktop computer and a netbook. The desktop computer is
an AMD with 8 cores of 3.1GHz each, 8 GB of RAM, a 1 GB graphic card
with hdmi output and a 120 GB SSD hard drive. Yes, it's a great
computer, so it's going to stay with me for a really long time.</p>

<p>
The other toy I've bought, the netbook, is an Asus eeepc of 10' with
two cores of 1.67GHz each, 1 GB of RAM and a hard drive of 250 GB,
more than enough to have mobility and a real computer for my
travels. I think that between the two toys I'm going to be very
productive, so I hope you'll see me more active in my projects and
around here.</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIP]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/10/30/RIP.html"/>
    <updated>2011-10-30T03:47:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/10/30/RIP</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
As you may now by now, this month had passed out three important
figures in the Computer Science world: Steve Jobs, Dennis Ritchie and
John McCarthy.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>
Steve Jobs is the most famous of them by the general public, but, at
the same time, the less influential in the Computer Science world. His
most important achieve has been to change the perception and use of
the technology of a lot of people. He was capable of innovate and
connect with the general public, but, in my point of view, he was
wrong about oe essential thing, the openness of his products. During
all his career, and specially during his last years, he has managed his
products in a closed way (he even didn't want to open the apple market
to independent developers!) and I think he has missed the opportunity
to really change the world if he would made free (as in freedom) at
least any of his products.</p>

<p>
Dennis Ritchie, as many of the articles has said about him, is one of
the original hackers. His great contribution (with other hackers) to
our world include the C programming language (probably the most used
programming language of all the times) and the Unix Operating System
(the same used by apple to develop Mac OS and used as a reference by
Richard M. Stallman and Linus Torvalds to develop GNU/Linux). This is
a perfect example of how a free software can influence in the world
(remember that Unix, at the beginnig, was open, and was after its
success when companies and organizations started to launch his own
closed version of Unix).</p>

<p>
The last one that have passed out is John McCarthy, creator of the
Lisp programming language and of the term Artificial Intelligence.
The Lisp programming language is less used than the C programming
language, but it has been the most used programming language in
Artificial Intelligence, in wich he is one of the major
contributors. He also was the first to publicly suggest that computer
time-sharing technology might lead to a future in which computing
power and even specific applications could be sold through the utility
business model.</p>

<p>
We're going to miss them and we'll try to continue their work the
better we can.</p>

<p>
RIP</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[#SpanishRevolution, part III]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/10/10/Spanish-Revolution-III.html"/>
    <updated>2011-10-10T00:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/10/10/Spanish-Revolution-III</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
In the <a href="https://blogs.fsfe.org/palvarez/2011/09/14/spanishrevolution-part-ii/">second part</a> of this post I've explained the recent history and
evolution of the social movements in Spain. In this post I'm going to
focus in #15m (or Indignados) movement, how they've started, their
proposals, things that, <b>IMHO</b>, they've done well, things to improve
and where they should go.</p>

<p>
As I said in my previous post, Indignados movement has been influenced
by the #nolesvotes movement, which shows both how to self-organize in
a global way (the opposite of the traditional social movements has
done historically, working at a neighborhood level or, at best, at a
city level) and how the new technologies can help in this
self-organization, but, obviously, it's not the only movement that has
influenced to #15M.</p>

<p>
In recent years the social movements in Spain have seen a revival in
grassroots organization, whose work in the neighborhoods has been an
essential breeding ground for movement #15M. These grassroots
organizations have a participatory democracy based on people's
assemblies and consensus decision making. These horizontally
structured assemblies are completely transparent and open to anyone
who wants to participate. The groundwork has served not only to learn
work techniques and methodologies assemblies, but also enabled them to
know the people, know their concerns and problems and know how to work
with them.</p>

<p>
Therefore, having these two movements as parents it's not strange how
quickly this movement has emerged and spread throughout all the country,
in a way that only a few people could imagine.</p>

<p>
On January 2011, the digital platform Democracia real YA (one of the
main actors in #15M movement) was created on Spanish social networks
and forums. Having the support of organisations such as ATTAC,
Intermon Oxfam, Ecologists in Action or Youth without Future, and
using Twitter and Facebook it called "the unemployed, poorly paid, the
subcontractors, the precarious, young people&#x2026;" to take the streets
on 15 May in almost every city in Spain (you have at Wikipedia a
comprehensive list of all the places that were called to take the
streets on that day). That same day, small demonstrations in support
of the Spanish ones were organised in Dublin, Lisbon, Amsterdam,
Istanbul, Bologna, London and Paris.</p>

<p>
The first protest was called under the motto "we are not goods in the
hands of politicians and bankers" and was focused on opposition to
what the protesters called "antisocial means in the hands of bankers",
partly referring to the changes made in 2010 to contain the ongoing
European sovereign debt crisis through bailout of the banks, which the
Spanish society saw as responsible for the crisis, while at the same
time the government kept announcing social program cutbacks.
Protesters also demanded more democracy, a new electoral law and end
to political corruption as well as other claims, such as banks
nationalisation.</p>

<p>
The main demand of #15M is a radical change in Spanish politics, and,
although #15M is a heterogeneous and ambiguous group, they share a
strong rejection of unemployment, welfare cuts, Spanish politicians,
the current two-party system in Spain between the Spanish Socialist
Workers' Party and the People's Party, as well as the current
political system, capitalism, banks and bankers, political corruption
and firmly support what they call basic rights: home, work, culture,
health and education.</p>

<p>
As #nolesvotes, they don't consider themselves to be represented by
any traditional party nor favoured by the measures approved by
politicians. If you want to know more about the #15M proposals and
actions you can visit their <a href="http://movimiento15m.org/">official page</a> and read their <a href="http://movimiento15m.org/manifiesto-movimiento-15m-%C2%A1democracia-real-ya/#more-5">manifesto</a>.</p>

<p>
The impact of #15M has been bigger than anyone thought, because
according to statistics published by RTVE (the Spanish public
broadcasting company) between 6.5 and 8 million Spaniards have
participated in these protests, an unthinkable thing at the beginning
of the year, and in this kind of things you can't trust the official
information, so probably the participation has been even more.</p>

<p>
I think the most important thing that this movement has made is to
make the spanish population aware that we can change the actual
situation of our country, because a lot of people didn't think they
can do something to make a change.</p>

<p>
Also, I think that #15M can have a life much longer than much people
can imagine, from one side because the changes they are proposing are
big ones, and they need time to define both the changes we have to
make to have a fairly society and the strategy to make this changes
possible, and from the other side because they have reach a big impact
in the population, a lot of people has been a part of #15M, and being
part of a movement like this makes you feel that your contribution is
important, and, although sometimes you can desperate, this is a
feeling that once you have it you want to keep it.</p>

<p>
Seeing the movement from the outside (although I wanted to involve
myself in the movement I couldn't find the time until now) I think
that sometimes they've enter in the politician's game more than they
needs, but, obviously, it's a new and complex situation to handle and
it can't be perfect.</p>

<p>
The movement has passed some critical times and situations (like the
time after the local elections or the Pope visit), and they'll going
to pass some more critical situations, but I think that the most
important one is to handle the people's mood (it's a long path and a
lot of people can desperate).</p>

<p>
Finally, although the movement can end in nothing, I think that the
process is very important, not only because we're trying to change
important thinks, but also because we are changing the point of view
of a lot of people that, until now, they didn't realize they can make
a change, and this is the seed of future revolutions.</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!</p>

<p>
P.D.: You can access to information about the 15-M movement at the
wikipedia <a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/es/wiki/Movimiento_15-M">here</a>, <a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/es/wiki/15M">here</a> (in spanish) and <a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/2011_Spanish_protests">here</a> (in english).</p>

<p>
P.P.D.: All the ideas I expose here are personal opinions, comming
only from myself, and here I don't represent any of the organizations
I belong to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[#SpanishRevolution, part II]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/09/14/Spanish-Revolution-II.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-14T02:10:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/09/14/Spanish-Revolution-II</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
In the <a href="https://blogs.fsfe.org/palvarez/2011/08/19/spanishrevolution-part-i/">first part</a> of this post I've explained the economical situation
of Spain and how we've reached this situation. Now it's the turn to
explain a little bit the origins of the Indignados movement ant the
recent history of the social movements in Spain.</p>

<p>
The Indignados movement (or #15M) born officially the 15 of May of
2011, although I think the real begining started before. In order to
understand better the origins of the #15M it's better to explain a
little bit the recent phistory of the social movements in Spain.</p>

<p>
As you might know, before the actual democracy Spain was headed by
Francisco Franco, a dictator aligned ideologically with Hitler. Some
years before his dead (1975) the social movements in Spain begans to
be very strong, and, although they had to be subversive (the
government was very represive even after the dead of Franco), they
gain a lot of popularity, specially in the young people.</p>

<p>
After 1975 and during the 80's Spain became into a cultural and
political revolution, and a lot of political parties (included PSOE
and the Comunist Party) and labor unions (CCOO, UGT, CNT, &#x2026;) were
legalized. This was the golden epoch of the social movements in Spain,
because a lot of people were conscious that it was important to be
part of the (not only) political change that was happening in Spain
and, a very important thing, they were a part of this changes, in part
because the government were taking them into consideration and making
changes in the way the social movements were saying.</p>

<p>
After that, during the final 80s and the 90s the political parties
forgot about the people and began to govern for themselves and for the
"markets" (a.k.a the rich people) and the social movements began to
accommodate, partially because the social situation were much better
than during the dictatorial period and partially because some state
mechanisms made the social movements too dependents from the
government charity, and in the moment that any organization depends
on the government it has to do some things and leave to do other
things to please them and survive.</p>

<p>
I think that the reaction to this circumstances come both from a new
social movement surged in Spain (and in the world :)), the Free
Software movement, that has become very strong sice the final 90s, and
from the deterioration of the spanish life style, specially with the
actual crisis environment.</p>

<p>
In the last years we've seen here in Spain a lot of movement against
the software patents in Europe and agains some copyright laws that
have emerged in the last years in Spain, and a big part of this
movement has been lead by hacktivist that have been participated in
the Free Software movement during several years.</p>

<p>
This movements have been organized dinamically, without a need of a
phisical organization, and in several times during a specific period
of time. This has made that the state, with his old mechanisms of
working, couldn't stop this kind of organization, that have made the
enough noise to influence again in the political life of the country
and in the spanish people.</p>

<p>
This was the kind of organization of #nolesvotes, the father of
the #15m (or indignados) movement, who asks to vote in the municipal
elections to any party but PSOE or PP, rised after the approval of an
unfair copyright law by the two main political parties of
Spain. Because of that #nolesvotes gained the support and/or
comprehension of the population, being, in my point of view, a big
success.</p>

<p>
To be continued&#x2026;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
