<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[General | Ritho's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/category/general/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/"/>
  <updated>2020-03-25T02:02:10+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.ritho.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[palvarez@ritho.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New job at Lana]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2020/01/05/new-job.html"/>
    <updated>2020-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2020/01/05/new-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
This year has come with an important change in my working side. In mid January
I've finished my work relationship with Zaleos, and, since the beginning of
March, I've started working at Lana.
</p>

<p>
As you know, in May I decided to come back to Spain, and I had to thank the
opportunity to Zaleos. I have learned a lot in Zaleos during the time I've worked
there, and I think they have a great team. Still, at some point, we had some
differences in our daily job and, finally, they decided to let me go. I think it
wasn't an easy decision for them. For me, besides the initial bad sensation (it
never feels good when any company let you go), I think it was a good decision
because I wasn't feeling too comfortable either. I think that probably with better
communication and some work we could make it work. Still, finally, it was their
decision, and I understand it.
</p>

<p>
On the bride side, I've started working at Lana since the beginning of March as
Senior Backend Developer. Lana is a Fintech that started inside Cabify with a
solution to disperse payments to the Cabify drivers, and it has some exciting
projects to grow the company. The backend stack is done entirely in Golang, using
technologies like Kubernetes or Elastic Search, and, since it's a new startup,
there's a lot of exciting work to do. The project has a bit more than two years,
so you can imagine the amount of work to do and new ideas we want to try. I hope
not only to learn a lot about technology and the financial business side but also
aport my knowledge and experience to the project. Since the tech team is split
into several locations (we have developers in Mexico, Chile, Amsterdam, Madrid,
Malaga, &#x2026;) I'll keep working from Cordoba, which is good news for me too :).
</p>

<p>
I have several pending posts about things I've learned in Zaleos about SIP, and
I'm sure I'll publish new blog posts related to my current work, so keep in the
loop.
</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving back to Spain]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2019/05/09/moving-back-to-spain.html"/>
    <updated>2019-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2019/05/09/moving-back-to-spain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Hi all,
</p>

<p>
After more than three and a half years in Mexico working at Segundamano Mexico,
I've decided to accept an offer from <a href="https://www.zaleos.net/">Zaleos</a> and come back to Spain. As you may
know, I've been working at Schibsted (the company that owns Segundamano) for
eight years, first in Madrid for four years and a half approximately and later
in Mexico City for the last three and a half years,. This time has been an
amazing time, both personally (I've met some great people, some of them will
remain friends in the future) and professionally (I can't even list all the
things I've learned during this time). But at a certain point, I felt that I
needed a new challenge to keep growing professionally. At the same time, I wanted
to be closer to my family, since we were more than 10000 km away, and that is
where Zaleos comes.
</p>

<p>
Zaleos is a software development company that develops IP based solutions to
provide to the Public Safety sector with the much-needed ability to interface
with multiple sources of data and receive critical, real-time information from
callers in need. I expect to see technologies related to VoIP and real-time
protocols, a full new field for me in the working environment, so don't be
surprised if I start posting entries about real-time protocols :).
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm Back!]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2013/09/17/back.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T18:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2013/09/17/back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Hi all!</p>

<p>
I know it hass been more than a year without writing anything, but, between my
absorving work and the fact that I'm not really good with the written world (and
a little bit of lazyness, why no admit it), I didn't found the time to dedicate
to the blog.</p>

<p>
Now I'm not going to give promises, but I'm going to try it hard to write at least
one post per week, and who knows, maybe once I've started to write I can write
more often and more fluently.</p>

<p>
Well, you'll have notices from me during this week.</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Latest adquisitionsn]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2012/03/03/latest-adquisitions.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-03T23:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2012/03/03/latest-adquisitions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Hi all!</p>

<p>
I'm back from South America (I've been 6 weeks in Chile and Argentina)
with some good and bad news. The bad new is that I've been stolen and
I don't have anymore some of my technical stuff, like a laptop, an
external hard drive, a tablet and some other things. I've also lost
some information, specially documentation and some projects of my
studies and previous works.</p>

<p>
The good thing is that I've to restore some of the things I've lost,
so I bought a desktop computer and a netbook. The desktop computer is
an AMD with 8 cores of 3.1GHz each, 8 GB of RAM, a 1 GB graphic card
with hdmi output and a 120 GB SSD hard drive. Yes, it's a great
computer, so it's going to stay with me for a really long time.</p>

<p>
The other toy I've bought, the netbook, is an Asus eeepc of 10' with
two cores of 1.67GHz each, 1 GB of RAM and a hard drive of 250 GB,
more than enough to have mobility and a real computer for my
travels. I think that between the two toys I'm going to be very
productive, so I hope you'll see me more active in my projects and
around here.</p>

<p>
Happy Hacking!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIP]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/10/30/RIP.html"/>
    <updated>2011-10-30T03:47:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.ritho.net/general/2011/10/30/RIP</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
As you may now by now, this month had passed out three important
figures in the Computer Science world: Steve Jobs, Dennis Ritchie and
John McCarthy.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>
Steve Jobs is the most famous of them by the general public, but, at
the same time, the less influential in the Computer Science world. His
most important achieve has been to change the perception and use of
the technology of a lot of people. He was capable of innovate and
connect with the general public, but, in my point of view, he was
wrong about oe essential thing, the openness of his products. During
all his career, and specially during his last years, he has managed his
products in a closed way (he even didn't want to open the apple market
to independent developers!) and I think he has missed the opportunity
to really change the world if he would made free (as in freedom) at
least any of his products.</p>

<p>
Dennis Ritchie, as many of the articles has said about him, is one of
the original hackers. His great contribution (with other hackers) to
our world include the C programming language (probably the most used
programming language of all the times) and the Unix Operating System
(the same used by apple to develop Mac OS and used as a reference by
Richard M. Stallman and Linus Torvalds to develop GNU/Linux). This is
a perfect example of how a free software can influence in the world
(remember that Unix, at the beginnig, was open, and was after its
success when companies and organizations started to launch his own
closed version of Unix).</p>

<p>
The last one that have passed out is John McCarthy, creator of the
Lisp programming language and of the term Artificial Intelligence.
The Lisp programming language is less used than the C programming
language, but it has been the most used programming language in
Artificial Intelligence, in wich he is one of the major
contributors. He also was the first to publicly suggest that computer
time-sharing technology might lead to a future in which computing
power and even specific applications could be sold through the utility
business model.</p>

<p>
We're going to miss them and we'll try to continue their work the
better we can.</p>

<p>
RIP</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
