<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <title><![CDATA[Coconet | Ritho's blog]]></title> <link href="http://blog.ritho.net/category/coconet/atom.xml" rel="self"/> <link href="http://blog.ritho.net/"/> <updated>2016-06-10T01:02:27-05:00</updated> <id>http://blog.ritho.net/</id> <author> <name><![CDATA[Ritho]]></name> <email><![CDATA[palvarez@ritho.net]]></email> </author> <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator> <entry> <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coconet 1.0.2 is out!]]></title> <link href="http://blog.ritho.net/2012/05/01/coconet-1.0.2/"/> <updated>2012-05-01T16:51:00-05:00</updated> <id>http://blog.ritho.net/2012/05/01/coconet-1.0.2</id> <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> Hi all!</p> <p> We have a new release of Coconet, in this case the version 1.0.2. In this step I've finished the translations into english of all the code (global variables, functions and structs) and I've made some extra optimizations of the code (nothing important).</p> <p> In the next days/weeks (I've to work and to advance in other projects :)) I'm going to port the project compilation process to autoconf and automake. I want also to start the refactoring of the code to remove at least some of the global variables and make some more important optimizations of it.</p> <p> If you want to try the latest stable version you can download it from <a href="https://github.com/i02sopop/coconet/tarball/v1.0.2">here</a>, and if you want to checkout the code from the repository and collaborate with me please visit the <a href="https://github.com/i02sopop/coconet">github repository page</a>.</p> <p> Happy Hacking!!!</p> ]]></content> </entry> <entry> <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coconet 1.0.1 is out!]]></title> <link href="http://blog.ritho.net/2012/03/04/coconet-1.0.1/"/> <updated>2012-03-04T00:03:00-06:00</updated> <id>http://blog.ritho.net/2012/03/04/coconet-1.0.1</id> <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> Hi all!</p> <p> Today (well, actually yesterday :)) I've launched Coconet 1.0.1, the first step to modernize my ending project at the University. In this first step I've translated the comments and part of the code (it left the functions name and the data structures) into english and I've made some little optimizations. I've also structured a little bit the project, but I've to add some additional information.</p> <p> My next steps are finishing the translation of all the code, make a review of all the code to enhace the design and optimize it, port the build of the project to autoconf and automake and make a simple web page of the project containing its basic information, some links to download the code (as a package and from the repository), &#x2026;</p> <p> If you want to try the latest stable version you can download it from <a href="https://github.com/i02sopop/coconet/tarball/v1.0.1">here</a>, and if you want to checkout the code from the repository and collaborate with me please visit the <a href="https://github.com/i02sopop/coconet">github repository page</a>.</p> <p> Happy Hacking!!!</p> ]]></content> </entry> </feed>